<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Misc on narrowfocus</title>
    <link>https://saurav1004.github.io/categories/misc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Misc on narrowfocus</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://saurav1004.github.io/categories/misc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Faithfulness vs Plausibility</title>
      <link>https://saurav1004.github.io/posts/faithfulness-vs-plausibility/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://saurav1004.github.io/posts/faithfulness-vs-plausibility/</guid>
      <description>In previous writeup on writing I talked briefly about the problem of plausibility vs faithfulness. I came across this core distinction while working with AI systems (particularly LLMs)&#xA;There has been quite some research in this area. Here are some key papers that highlight the problem :&#xA;Chain-of-Thought Reasoning In The Wild Is Not Always Faithful link Language Models Don&amp;rsquo;t Always Say What They Think: Unfaithful Explanations in Chain-of-Thought Promptinglink Reasoning Models Don&amp;rsquo;t Always Say What They Think link When Chain of Thought is Necessary, Language Models Struggle to Evade Monitors link The Probabilities Also Matter link Faithfulness of LLM Self-Explanations for Commonsense Tasks link Walk the Talk [link](Walk the Talk) The core distinction is that faithfulness is a measure of truth, whereas plausibility is a measure of persuasiveness.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faithfulness vs Plausibility</title>
      <link>https://saurav1004.github.io/posts/information-theoretic-metrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://saurav1004.github.io/posts/information-theoretic-metrics/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faithfulness vs Plausibility</title>
      <link>https://saurav1004.github.io/posts/transformer-computation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://saurav1004.github.io/posts/transformer-computation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Writing</title>
      <link>https://saurav1004.github.io/posts/onwriting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://saurav1004.github.io/posts/onwriting/</guid>
      <description>On Writing as a Tool for Thought # If people cannot write well, they cannot think well, and if they cannot think well, others will do their thinking for them.&#xA;Writing is, for many, a formidable task. The difficulty often stems not from the mechanics of language but from a dual uncertainty: a lack of clarity about the subject and an anxiety about how their words will shape perception. There have been countless pieces of writing on how to overcome these problems.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RL for LLMs</title>
      <link>https://saurav1004.github.io/posts/rl-for-llms/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://saurav1004.github.io/posts/rl-for-llms/</guid>
      <description>The year of 2024 was of RL algorithms. Numerous new algorithms were applied for Reinforcement Learning of Large Language Models. As someone working with these methods or LLMs in general, it becomes crucial to understand the internals of these algorithms and how they relate to each other. And not just that, but answering why did we do that small change, was it really necessary, was it worth it ? and so on.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical Stability in Pytorch</title>
      <link>https://saurav1004.github.io/posts/numerical-stability/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://saurav1004.github.io/posts/numerical-stability/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ndash; old post &amp;ndash; # &amp;ndash; maintainence notice : I wrote this post long back, and have moved multiple templates / static site generators in the meantime. Most expressions should just work fine. But it might be breaking in some places, thanks for bearing with it. &amp;ndash; # The core of training a deep neural network is gradient-based optimization. We calculate how the model&amp;rsquo;s error changes with respect to each of its millions (or billions) of parameters and take a small step in the direction that reduces that error.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Log Sum Exp in Pytorch</title>
      <link>https://saurav1004.github.io/posts/log-sum-exp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://saurav1004.github.io/posts/log-sum-exp/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ndash; old post &amp;ndash; # &amp;ndash; maintainence notice : I wrote this post long back, and have moved multiple templates / static site generators in the meantime. Most expressions should just work fine. But it might be breaking in some places, thanks for bearing with it. &amp;ndash; # When working with PyTorch for classification tasks, you&amp;rsquo;ll encounter a common pattern: your model outputs raw scores (called logits), and you feed these directly into a loss function like nn.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Realist’s Manifesto</title>
      <link>https://saurav1004.github.io/posts/realist/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://saurav1004.github.io/posts/realist/</guid>
      <description>The Realist’s Manifesto:&#xA;Human beings are trapped in endless cycles of introspection. Realism breaks this cycle by driving people to take action and move forward. Realism values shorter feedback loops, leading to faster iterations and deeper understanding. It insists on a bias for action and the need for testability. Fail fast and learn. Actions are rooted in simple systems and first principles. Systems are built from basic, fundamental, measurable elements called the primitives.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
